<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugo on whatacold&#39;s space</title>
    <link>https://whatacold.io/tags/hugo/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Hugo on whatacold&#39;s space</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <managingEditor>whatacold@gmail.com (whatacold)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>whatacold@gmail.com (whatacold)</webMaster>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 25 Nov 2023 12:44:53 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://whatacold.io/tags/hugo/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Hugo Blogging in Emacs</title>
      <link>https://whatacold.io/blog/2022-10-10-emacs-hugo-blogging/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2022 22:50:48 +0800</pubDate><author>whatacold@gmail.com (whatacold)</author>
      <guid>https://whatacold.io/blog/2022-10-10-emacs-hugo-blogging/</guid>
      <description>When I started to use Hugo to write this blog last year, I noticed that there is an easy-hugo package of Emacs that there are many people use it. So I installed it that time, but I didn&amp;#39;t use many of its features along the way. The only command I used was easy-hugo-current-time. I used it to update the Hugo timestamps manually as in the format of 2022-10-15T09:45:35+08:00.&#xA;My most desirable feature is to use it to select tags easily when I start to write a new post, but I never got it to work.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>illustrate.clj to Illustrate Clojure Snippet</title>
      <link>https://whatacold.io/blog/2021-08-07-illustrate-clojure-snippet/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Aug 2021 18:49:25 +0800</pubDate><author>whatacold@gmail.com (whatacold)</author>
      <guid>https://whatacold.io/blog/2021-08-07-illustrate-clojure-snippet/</guid>
      <description>To get my hands dirty with Clojure, I am trying to find or implement Clojure&amp;#39;s string functions in the sense of Python. Python has powerful string APIs, and I also want to see how powerful Clojure could be in this field. That would be interesting.&#xA;As shown in the cheatsheet, Clojure has implemented most of them, and there are some that I have to implement myself, like title-case.&#xA;Along the way, I found it was a little cumbersome to append the evaluation result and the result of calling them, for example,</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
