<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Linux on Ken Huang</title>
    <link>https://whatacold.io/tags/linux/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Linux on Ken Huang</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <managingEditor>whatacold@gmail.com (Ken Huang)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>whatacold@gmail.com (Ken Huang)</webMaster>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:11:19 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://whatacold.io/tags/linux/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Adjust the laptop&#39;s screen brightness in Emacs</title>
      <link>https://whatacold.io/blog/2022-05-21-adjust-screen-brightness-emacs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 May 2022 11:50:25 +0800</pubDate><author>whatacold@gmail.com (Ken Huang)</author>
      <guid>https://whatacold.io/blog/2022-05-21-adjust-screen-brightness-emacs/</guid>
      <description>Adjust the screen brightness in Emacs If you&amp;#39;re using i3wm on Linux, how do you adjust the laptop&amp;#39;s screen brightness?&#xA;Most of the time, I use the laptop with an external monitor. But when I am out, I have no monitors. And it seems no easy way to adjust the brightness in i3wm. Being too bright or dim is terrible for the eyes.&#xA;Recently, I found a command-line tool called brightnessctl, which can adjust the brightness in a terminal.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to Reload i3status config On the Fly</title>
      <link>https://whatacold.io/blog/2022-01-14-i3wm-i3status-reload-config/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jan 2022 22:36:13 +0800</pubDate><author>whatacold@gmail.com (Ken Huang)</author>
      <guid>https://whatacold.io/blog/2022-01-14-i3wm-i3status-reload-config/</guid>
      <description>Sometimes I want to change the status (i3status) of i3wm temporarily, but it seems that i3wm doesn&amp;#39;t support it directly, although reloading the config for i3wm itself is a piece of cake (bindsym $mod+Shift+c reload in the config, or i3-msg -t command reload in the command line).&#xA;But this issue scratched my itch, and I swear that I must solve it today.&#xA;Following this Reddit post, it looks like it can be done by restarting the process of i3bar:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Send Notifications from Emacs with i3wm and Dunst</title>
      <link>https://whatacold.io/blog/2021-07-17-emacs-i3wm-dunst/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Jul 2021 12:22:10 +0800</pubDate><author>whatacold@gmail.com (Ken Huang)</author>
      <guid>https://whatacold.io/blog/2021-07-17-emacs-i3wm-dunst/</guid>
      <description>I barely use notifications, but recently I think it&amp;#39;s a valuable way to remind me things like helping me nurture habits, or to notify me of emergencies like a critically low laptop battery.&#xA;So I try to integrate notifications to org-mode and Emacs today.&#xA;The org-notify package from org-contrib (install it by (package-install &amp;#39;org-contrib) ) could do this job easily before, so I first test it in the minibuffer with (org-notify &amp;#34;test&amp;#34;).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Open New Urxvt from within Emacs</title>
      <link>https://whatacold.io/blog/2019-11-25-start-a-new-urxvt-terminal-on-emacs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2019 22:47:00 +0800</pubDate><author>whatacold@gmail.com (Ken Huang)</author>
      <guid>https://whatacold.io/blog/2019-11-25-start-a-new-urxvt-terminal-on-emacs/</guid>
      <description>I have been really enjoying the more concentration workflow qtile, a tiling window manager, brings me, since I started using it a few months ago. I am more focus on the current task now as all the windows I care about are laid out on the same screen.&#xA;As I get more used to qtile at every day&amp;#39;s work, I noticed that I became more depend on short-life terminal sessions.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
