<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>tiling-wm on whatacold&#39;s Space</title>
    <link>https://whatacold.io/tags/tiling-wm/</link>
    <description>Recent content in tiling-wm on whatacold&#39;s Space</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <managingEditor>whatacold@gmail.com (whatacold)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>whatacold@gmail.com (whatacold)</webMaster>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 17 Jul 2021 12:22:10 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://whatacold.io/tags/tiling-wm/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Send Notifications from Emacs with i3wm and Dunst</title>
      <link>https://whatacold.io/blog/2021-07-17-emacs-i3wm-dunst/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Jul 2021 12:22:10 +0800</pubDate>
      <author>whatacold@gmail.com (whatacold)</author>
      <guid>https://whatacold.io/blog/2021-07-17-emacs-i3wm-dunst/</guid>
      <description>I barely use notifications, but recently I think it&amp;#39;s a valuable way to remind me things like helping me nurture habits, or to notify me of emergencies like a critically low laptop battery.
 So I try to integrate notifications to org-mode and Emacs today.
 I knew the built-in org-notify could do this job easily before, so I first test it in the minibuffer with (org-notify &amp;#34;test&amp;#34;).
 Unfortunately, it errors out:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Manage SSH Connections with ~/.ssh/config</title>
      <link>https://whatacold.io/blog/2019-12-22-manage-ssh-connections-with-ssh-config/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Dec 2019 18:52:00 +0800</pubDate>
      <author>whatacold@gmail.com (whatacold)</author>
      <guid>https://whatacold.io/blog/2019-12-22-manage-ssh-connections-with-ssh-config/</guid>
      <description>I used to manage SSH connection with such GUI apps as MobaXterm, when I wrote code on Windows at work. As I changed my workflow to use a tiling window manager in a VirtualBox guest OS, I continued to improve my way of managing SSH connections, which I want to share here if you don&amp;#39;t know yet.
 At first, I baked a helper Python script, which I named as qssh for &amp;#34;quick ssh&amp;#34;, to help me assemble ssh arguments for me(such as username, Ip, port, etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Start a New Terminal(urxvt) at Current Buffer&#39;s default-directory on Emacs</title>
      <link>https://whatacold.io/blog/2019-11-25-start-a-new-urxvt-terminal-on-emacs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2019 22:47:00 +0800</pubDate>
      <author>whatacold@gmail.com (whatacold)</author>
      <guid>https://whatacold.io/blog/2019-11-25-start-a-new-urxvt-terminal-on-emacs/</guid>
      <description>I have been really enjoying the more concentration workflow qtile, a tiling window manager, brings me, since I started using it a few months ago. I am more focus on the current task now as all the windows I care about are laid out on the same screen.
 As I get more used to qtile at every day&amp;#39;s work, I noticed that I became more depend on short-life terminal sessions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How To Run Bleeding-edge Qtile Within a Virtualenv</title>
      <link>https://whatacold.io/blog/2019-09-29-how-to-run-the-bleeding-edge-code-of-qtile/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Sep 2019 17:05:00 +0800</pubDate>
      <author>whatacold@gmail.com (whatacold)</author>
      <guid>https://whatacold.io/blog/2019-09-29-how-to-run-the-bleeding-edge-code-of-qtile/</guid>
      <description>For having been using GNOME for quite a long time, I was considering trying some tiling window managers to see what it&amp;#39;s like a few weeks ago. Along the way, I found a nice window manager written in Python: Qtile, what interests me most is that it&amp;#39;s a hackable window manager, which makes it flexible to extend or change its behaviors.
 Well, switching to use a tiling window manager is far simpler than I thought.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
