<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Git on whatacold&#39;s space</title>
    <link>https://whatacold.io/tags/git/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Git on whatacold&#39;s space</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <managingEditor>whatacold@gmail.com (whatacold)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>whatacold@gmail.com (whatacold)</webMaster>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2020 18:48:00 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://whatacold.io/tags/git/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Binary Search Idea for Narrowing Down Problem Space</title>
      <link>https://whatacold.io/blog/2020-02-04-binary-search-algorithm-vs-problem-solving/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2020 18:48:00 +0800</pubDate>
      <author>whatacold@gmail.com (whatacold)</author>
      <guid>https://whatacold.io/blog/2020-02-04-binary-search-algorithm-vs-problem-solving/</guid>
      <description>Binary search algorithm is a search algorithm that finds the position of a target value within a sorted array. It cuts off the target array in half in a pass, so that it has a worst-case performance of O(log n).
Visualization of the binary search algorithm where 7 is the target value(@wikipedia) We all know that it&amp;#39;s an efficient searching algorithm, but the strategy behind it also applies for narrowing down other problem space, for example, finding out when a bug is first introduced in a series of git commits.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Can&#39;t Git Fetch Remote Branches Other Than Master?</title>
      <link>https://whatacold.io/blog/2019-12-01-why-cant-git-fetch-remote-branches-other-than-master/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2019 16:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      <author>whatacold@gmail.com (whatacold)</author>
      <guid>https://whatacold.io/blog/2019-12-01-why-cant-git-fetch-remote-branches-other-than-master/</guid>
      <description>Last week I came into a problem with Git, that I can&amp;#39;t fetch the remote branch that I just pushed to. It was so weird because I can push it. It never happens before, and it happened when I was in a rush to rebase my code, as someone in my team pushed his code.
After searching, it seemed that the configuration of fetch of that repo was different(this Stack Overflow thread for example) than before, it was specified that only master can be fetched.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How To Revert a Series of Git Commits?</title>
      <link>https://whatacold.io/blog/2019-09-24-how-to-revert-a-series-of-commits-with-git/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2019 23:14:00 +0800</pubDate>
      <author>whatacold@gmail.com (whatacold)</author>
      <guid>https://whatacold.io/blog/2019-09-24-how-to-revert-a-series-of-commits-with-git/</guid>
      <description>Sometimes, I need to revert a series of commits that I&amp;#39;ve already pushed, doing a git hard reset (git reset --hard) is not an option, as someone may already have new commits based on mine.
For example, assume that I&amp;#39;ve made a few commits like below:
65a2c62 * commit 10 25cad43 * commit 9 72ad583 * commit 8 ceebf9a * commit 7 acf8a11 * commit 6 28d526f * commit 5 63af1e2 * commit 4 982c71c * commit 3 0fb4c2d * commit 2 acf9da1 * commit 1 b5f9933 * commit 0 For whatever reason, I need to &amp;#34;drop&amp;#34; the changes made by commit 6 to commit 10, that is, go back to &amp;#34;commit 5&amp;#34; without deleting these commits.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
